Miguel Marques Simões

Summary

Software engineer with 4+ years of experience, proficient in multiple programming languages, frameworks, and embedded systems. Great troubleshooting skills and focused on delivering clean, error free, reliable code. Passion to work in a collaborative team, sharing and cooperating with like-minded people with different views in a varied environment.

Work Experience

Mid-level Software Engineer 05/2022 – Present

Abusix, Germany - Remote

Currently I work as a Software Engineer in the Dataservices team from Abusix. I'm responsible for the development of software that mitigates network abuse and other cyber threats. The software identifies patterns of abuse in the reports that reach our honeypots (phishing, malware, spam, botnet, etc) and produces events with all the relevant information to be used later by other products of the company. I'm also accountable for accomplishing code reviews since we work in a CI/CD environment and we do value code quality a lot.

During my career at Abusix I've been given the opportunity to take ownership of a new project that uses ML and AI to improve the existing software, which is something that fulfils my passion for Intelligent Systems.

Junior Software Engineer 11/2020 – 05/2022

Deloitte, Portugal

At Deloitte I worked as a software engineer in the Financial Services Industry Consulting Division at Deloitte. During my career at Deloitte, I did work with Canadian Insurance companies.

My participation was predominantly in migration projects building software, mostly based in SQL data migrations (ETL), which allowed the clients to upgrade their business by migrating their legacy data to new, most reliable, low latency platforms.

Contacts

(+351) 965061991

miguel simoes@outlook.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/miguelmsimoes/

https://gitlab.com/miguel.simoes

https://github.com/simoesmiguel

Skills

Programming Languages and Frameworks:

Python (including Django, FastAPI, Flask), Typescript, JavaScript (including NodeJS), Java, SpringBoot

Database Technologies:

SQL, PostgreSQL

Cloud Services and Infrastructure:

AWS, Docker

Tools and Technologies:

Git, ETL, Grafana, Qlik Sense, Streamlit

APIs and Web Services:

REST APIs

Education and Training

Master's Degree in Information Systems and Computer Engineering (Specialization in Intelligent Systems), 2018-2020

Instituto Superior Técnico (Lisbon, Portugal)
https://fenix.tecnico.ulisboa.pt/cursos/meic-a

Bachelor's in Computer Engineering, 2015-2018

 University of Aveiro (Aveiro, Portugal) https://www.ua.pt/en/curso/486

Academic Works

Master's Thesis: Recommender System for Personalized Teaching Strategies - 18 values

Development of a Recommender System capable of suggesting specific course activities in the interest of supporting the student's ascendance helping them to succeed in the course. The Recommender System employed two different strategies to accomplish its goal, the first strategy was based on a Collaborative Filtering approach, whilst the second one followed a Reinforcement Learning plan. The results proved that no matter the strategy used, most of the students would benefit from a Recommender System that was capable of suggesting specific activities in order to help their ascendance to the upper profiles.

Keywords: Educational Data Mining, Recommender Systems, Reinforcement Learning, Gamification

Publications

A Recommender System For Personalized Teaching Strategies

GameCourse employs a blended learning approach in such a way that students attend both practical labs and theoretical classes while participating in discussions and completing online projects and assignments by Moodle.

Published at:

https://fenix.tecnico.ulisboa.pt/cursos/meic-a/dissertacao/1128253548922114

https://gamecourse.wixsite.com/inescid/publications

Certifications

FastAPI (Udemy) - 2023

Understanding Typescript (Udemy) - 2023

AWS Cloud Practitioner (Udemy) - 2022

Achievements

Shiftappens Portugal Hackathon

2018 - 1°st place

Member of the winning team of Shiftappens Portugal Hackathon, organized by Jeknowledge, a company of FCTUC.

The idea was to build a social network where the users were able to share both their personal data and media with predefined friends, in a private, encrypted, and secure way.

https://shiftappens.com/